Register of the Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty corporate records
Hoover Institution Archives
The Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty corporate records at the Hoover Institution Library and Archives includes extensive correspondence between Free Europe Committee (FEC) and American Committee for Liberation from Bolshevism (AMCOMLB) officials and Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) officials. From 1949 to 1959 this correspondence was conducted using pseudonyms. Thereafter, until CIA oversight ended in 1971, it was conducted anonymously between "The President" [FEC or AMCOMLIB] and "The Executive Committee," "Advisory Committee," or "Board of Trustees" [CIA]. This appendix provides the identification of the FEC officials who wrote in pseudonym and the identification of those CIA officials responsible for FEC and AMCOMLIB issues whose true names and pseudonyms have been released by CIA. Identification of persons referenced in the correspondence indicates their organizational role and authority and helps in assessing the significance of the documents.
Free Europe Committee Officials
PSEUDONYM
REAL NAME
John Free
DeWitt C. Poole
William Freely
Frederic R. Dolbeare
William L. Digby
Spencer Phoenix
Merton T. Stone
Frank Altschul
Kenneth J. Walters
Robert E. Lang
Frank C. Kilday
John Schroeder
Charles Dempsey
Herbert Gross
Albert Robinson
William E. Griffith
H. Adams
Alfred W. Held
Michael J. Peters
J. Barry Mahool
Ray D. Tarlston
Ray E. Millard
Thorne E. Minett
Ray E. Millard
James C. Hayden
James R. Burton
Thomas E. Marschal
Thomas E. Myers
Michael E. Thompson
Thomas E. Myers
John L. Damewood
H. Gates Lloyd
Marc Petticord
John Leich
John L. Waterfield
C. D. Jackson
Bischop E. Dodge
Lewis Galantiere
Dorothy J. Lucker
Ann Hester
Sam E. Teslove
Nancy Viccellio
Leonard I. Stamm
Admiral H. B. Miller
Thaddeus Z. Abernathy
Abbot Washburn
Walter Edson
Edward Welch
Martin C. Johnson
J. Clayton Miller
Paul Dexter
Stetson S. Holmes
James W. Nicholson
Konrad Kellen
Douglas Neich
Theodore C. Augustine
David Powers
Samuel S. Walker
Whiting Stratton
Levering Tyson
Bruce Farmer
Bernard Yarrow
Judith Flint
Irene Hood
Daniel Church
Whitney Shephardson
Robert C. Newton
George P. E. Cesar
William Melville
Richard M. Hunt
Joseph P. Bradford
Lawrence E. De Neufville
Mrs. Ruth D. Cobedent
Barbara G. Bowen
John J. Sullivan
Joseph F. Glennon
Frank Lloyd
Frank Wright
Owen Taylor
Thomas E. Brown Jr.
Travis A. Albery
Robert F. Kelley
Martin L. Cantwell
Robert F. Kelley
Carey Metcalfe
W. J. Convery Egan
Franklin Woorham
Frederick T. Merrill
James P. O'Brien
Robert F. Byrnes
Robert G. Bixley
Francis M. Hand
Walter P. O' Dwyer
Willis D. Crittenberger
CIA Officials Overseeing RFE and RL (Partial List)
PSEUDONYM
PERSON
Robert A. Ascham
Allen Dulles, Director of Central Intelligence
Harold S. Witting
Frank Wisner, Deputy Director for Plans
not released
Tom Braden, Chief, International Organizations Division (IOD), 1951-1954
not released
Cord Meyer, Chief, IOD, 1954-1957
William D. Playton
Tracy Barnes, Chief, Political and Psychological Warfare Division
Eliot B. Judane
Emmons Brown (IOD)
Philip D. Abramson
Emmons Brown (IOD)
not released
Robert "Bob" King (IOD)
not released
Harry Reis (IOD)
not released
John C. Richards (IOD)
not released
Arthur Cox (IOD)
not released
James "Jim" William Brown (IOD)
not released
Ernest I. Harrison (IOD)
not released
Arne Ekstrom (IOD)
Radio Free Europe.; Radio Liberty.; Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Radio broadcasting--Soviet Union.
- PUBLIC AFFAIRS OFFICE FILE, 1950-1995 (Boxes 1-74)
  Scope and Contents note
  Addresses and telephone numbers, advertisements, agreements, award file, buildings file, by-laws, code, clippings, correspondence, daily broadcast analysis file, engineering file, fact sheets, financial documents, guest books, history file, indexes, legal appraisal, lists, logos and logotypes, manuals, memoranda, minutes of meetings, mission statement, organizational charts, pension plan file, personnel file, press releases, profile file, publications (in-house), reports, schedules, speeches, and subject file, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  Container List
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the PUBLIC AFFAIRS OFFICE FILE
- PUBLIC AFFAIRS PHOTOGRAPHIC FILE, 1945-1996 (Boxes 75-140 (photo shelves))
  Prints and negatives depicting people and events associated with RFE/RL, Inc. and the history of the Cold War, arranged by subject.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the PUBLIC AFFAIRS PHOTOGRAPHIC FILE
- ALPHABETICAL FILE, 1948-1988 (Boxes 141-365)
  Materials from the Washington, D.C. office of RFE/RL, arranged in alphabetical order under original headings.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the ALPHABETICAL FILE
- OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT FILE, 1951-1995 (Boxes 366-412)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed matter, reports, schedules.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT FILE
- OFFICE OF THE EXECUTIVE VICE-PRESIDENT FILE, 1958-1994 (Boxes 413-433)
  Agreements, broadcast analysis reports, by-laws, cables, clippings, contracts, correspondence, financial records, inter-office communications, litigation records, memoranda, personnel records, policy guidelines, professional codes, reports, schedules, scripts, and travel records, arranged alphabetically by original heading.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the OFFICE OF THE EXECUTIVE VICE-PRESIDENT FILE
- OFFICE OF THE DIRECTOR OF MANAGEMENT FILE, 1989-1994 (Boxes 434-437)
  Briefing books, contracts, correspondence, financial documents, memoranda, and reports, arranged alphabetically by original heading.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the OFFICE OF THE DIRECTOR OF MANAGEMENT FILE
- OFFICE OF THE POLICY DIRECTOR FILE, 1950-1972 (Boxes 437-444)
  Daily guidance summaries, guidance notes, guidances, policy guidance memoranda, policy notes, and special guidances, arranged alphabetically by physical form and chronologically thereunder.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the OFFICE OF THE POLICY DIRECTOR FILE
- PROGRAM EVALUATION FILE, 1979-1994 (Boxes 445-468)
  BIB-commissioned evaluations of programming and program reviews, arranged alphabetically by broadcast department and language service.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the PROGRAM EVALUATION FILE
- AUDIENCE RESEARCH REPORTS, 1954-1996 (Boxes 469-570)
  Analytic memos, assessment memoranda, research memoranda, reports, and summaries, arranged by organizational hierarchy (EEAOR, MOR and SAAOR), alphabetically by physical form, and numerically and chronologically thereunder.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the AUDIENCE RESEARCH REPORTS
- AUDIENCE RESEARCH OFFICE FILE, 1958-1990, 2005 (Boxes 571-654)
  Arranged by organizational hierarchy (EEAOR, MOR and SAAOR), alphabetically by physical form, and numerically and chronologically thereunder.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the AUDIENCE RESEARCH OFFICE FILE
- AUDIENCE RESEARCH SURVEYS, 1945-2001 (Boxes 655-1655)
  Data related to audience research, polls and questionnaires, audience mail, reports, and statistics, organized by issuing individual or organization and chronologically thereunder.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the AUDIENCE RESEARCH SURVEYS
- HISTORICAL FILE, 1949-1995 (Boxes 1655-1887)
  Artificial series created by RFE/RL staff in 1995 for proposed history of the organization.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the HISTORICAL FILE
- RESEARCH FILE, 1966-1993 (Boxes on shelf)
  In process.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RESEARCH FILE
- RALPH WALTER FILE, 1951-1993 (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RALPH WALTER FILE
- WILLIAM ROBINSON FILE, 1964-1994 (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the WILLIAM ROBINSON FILE
- RADIO FREE EUROPE DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE, 1974-1994 (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RADIO FREE EUROPE DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE
- RADIO FREE EUROPE DEPUTY DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE, 1976-1996 (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RADIO FREE EUROPE DEPUTY DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE
- RADIO LIBERTY DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE, 1965-1995 (Boxes on shelf)
  The documents in this series relate primarily to S. Enders Wimbush’s and Kevin Klose’s tenures as RL Director. Most files consist solely of correspondence and memoranda. Other significant document types are mentioned when present. In process.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RADIO LIBERTY DIRECTOR'S OFFICE FILE
- CONTROLLERS OFFICE FILE (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the CONTROLLERS OFFICE FILE
- RFE/RL, INC. FILE, 1950-2006 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to the corporate, legislative, financial, and administrative activities of RFE/RL, Inc. conducted by the Washington, DC office staff, primarily created after the merging of Radio Free Europe, Radio Liberty, and the Free Europe Committee.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RFE/RL, INC. FILE
- FREE EUROPE, INC. FILE, 1949-1977 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to the corporate, legislative, financial, and administrative activities of Free Europe, Inc. conducted by the Washington, DC office staff, primarily created prior to the merging of Radio Free Europe, Radio Liberty, and the Free Europe Committee.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the FREE EUROPE, INC. FILE
- RADIO LIBERTY, INC. FILE, 1951-1977 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to the corporate, legislative, financial, and administrative activities of Radio Liberty, Inc. conducted by the Washington, DC office staff, primarily created after the merging of Radio Free Europe, Radio Liberty, and the Free Europe Committee.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RADIO LIBERTY, INC. FILE
- BROADCASTING BOARD OF GOVERNORS FILE, 1996-1998 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to the Broadcasting Board of Governors' oversight of RFE/RL, Inc. activities.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the BROADCASTING BOARD OF GOVERNORS FILE
- BOARD FOR INTERNATIONAL BROADCASTING FILE, 1973-1997 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to the Board for International Broadcasting's oversight of RFE/RL, Inc. activities.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the BOARD FOR INTERNATIONAL BROADCASTING FILE
- RFE/RL FUND, INC. FILE, 1950-1994 (Boxes on shelf)
  Contains materials related to fundraising programs, policy, and planning on the part of the Board of Directors and RFE/RL, Inc. staff.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RFE/RL FUND, INC. FILE
- WEST EUROPEAN ADVISORY COMMITTEE FILE, 1957-1993 (Boxes on shelf)
  Consists of documents related to the activities carried out by West European Advisory Committee (WEAC) members, with the bulk of the series consisting of correspondence and meeting materials.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the WEST EUROPEAN ADVISORY COMMITTEE FILE
- UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT FILE, 1959-1994 (Boxes on shelf)
  Consists of materials related to legislation, correspondence with congressmen and other government officials, and congressional records concerning the funding and policies of RFE, RL and RFE/RL, Inc.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT FILE
- RFE/RL RESEARCH INSTITUTE FILE, 1988-1994 (Boxes on shelf)
  Consists of materials concerning the administration, policies, and public relations of the RFE/RL Research Institute, as well, as background research documents.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the RFE/RL RESEARCH INSTITUTE FILE
- INTERNATIONAL BROADCAST SYSTEMS, INC. FILE, 1986-1996 (Boxes on shelf)
  Consists of materials related to the Israel Radio Relay station, including contract negotiations, planning, technical specifications, and litigation.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the INTERNATIONAL BROADCAST SYSTEMS, INC. FILE
- MUNICH/PRAGUE OFFICE FILE, 1951-1999 (Boxes on shelf)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the MUNICH/PRAGUE OFFICE FILE
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Photo shelves)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the PHOTOGRAPHS
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1950s-1980s (Oversize shelving)
  Albums, computer printouts, photographs, scrapbooks, and other materials, arranged by series provenance and thereunder by subject. In process.
- MICROPRINT FILE (MICROFICHE and MICROFILM), 1950-1995 (Photo shelves)
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the MICROPRINT FILE (MICROFICHE and MICROFILM)
- MOVING IMAGE MATERIALS, 1950-2005 (Film shelves)
  Access
  All original film reels are closed to researchers for preservation purposes. Use copies on VHS tape are available.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the MOVING IMAGE MATERIALS
- SOUND RECORDINGS, 1951- (Tape shelves)
  Focus group recordings, interviews, religious sermons, theme music, ethnic folk songs and classical music. Many of the folk and classical music recordings appear on phonograph discs (78 RPM) with RFE-produced, "Crusade for Freedom"-branded labelling. Languages include: Albanian, Bulgarian, Czech, English, Hungarian, Polish, and Romanian.
- PRINTED MATTER, 1953-1976 (Reading room workstation)